《霍比特人》
亲爱的佛罗多
My dear Frodo.
你曾问我 是否把我所有的冒险经历都告诉你了
You asked me once if I had told you everything there was to know about my adventures.
但当我告诉你我说的都是事实的时候…
And while I can honestly say I have told you the truth…
却没有告诉你事实的全部
I may not have told you all of it.
我现在老了 佛罗多
I am old now Frodo.
不再是过去那个霍比特人了
I'm not the same hobbit I once was.
我想是到了把一切都告诉你的时候了
I think it is time for you to know what really happened.
那是很久以前的事情了
It began long ago.
有一块离东方很远的土地
In a land far away to the East.
现在已经消失了
The like of which you will not find in the world today.
有一座城市叫做达尔
There was the city of Dale.
它的集市远近闻名 物美价廉
Its market's known far and wide, full of the bounties of fine and vail,
繁荣昌盛
peaceful and prosperous.
因为这座城市在中土之地最伟大的国家
For this city laid before the doors of the greatest kingdom in Middle-earth…
伊鲁柏
Erebor.
是山下之王索尔的要塞
Stronghold of Thror, king under the mountain.
他是最强大的矮人之王
The mightiest of the dwarf lords.
索尔对自己的统治很有信心 从未担心过家族血脉会断绝
Thror ruled with utter surety, never doubting his house would endure,
王位传给他的儿子
or his line lay secure in the lives of his son…
儿子又传给孙子
and grandson.
啊 佛罗多 伊鲁柏
Ah, Frodo. Erebor.
这座建在大山深处的城堡
Built deep within the mountain itself,
它的美无与伦比
the beauty of this fortress city was a legend.
它的财富都深埋在地下 贮存了大量宝石
Its wealth lay in the earth, in precious gems humed from rock,
矿石中金子多如泉涌
and in great seams of gold running like rivers through stone.
矮人的工艺举世无双
The skill of the dwarves was unequaled.
精美绝伦
Fashioning object of great beauty,
能用钻石 祖母绿 红宝石和蓝宝石制作精美饰品
out of diamond, emerald, ruby and sapphire.
当他们继续向下采掘
Ever they delved deeper down into the dark,
他们发现了它
and that is where they found it.
山之心
The heart of the mountain…
家传宝钻
The Arkenstone.
索尔赐它国王之宝的名号
Thror named it the king's jewel.
他用它作为君权神授的象征
He took it as a sign, a sign that his right to rule was divine.
所有人都必须向他致敬 包括精灵王瑟兰督伊
All would pay homage to him. Even the great Elven king, Thranduil.
但太平富足之年并未持久
But the years of peace and plenty were not to last.
日子开始变坏
Slowly the days turned sour,
让人警惕的夜幕降临
and the watchful nights closed in.
索尔对黄金的爱变得狂热起来
Thror's love of gold had grown too fierce…
内心开始变得病态
A sickness had begun to grow within him.
这是一种精神上的病态
It was a sickness of the mind.
当这种病态壮大
And where sickness thrives…
厄运开始降临
bad things will follow.
他们开始听到北方有飓风一样的声音传来
The first they heard was a noise like a hurricane, coming down from the North.
山上的松树在热风中摇晃
The pines on the mountain creaked and cracked in the hot dry wind.
巴林 拉响警报
Balin, sound the alarm.
把守卫叫来 马上
Call out the guards, do it now!
那是什么？
What is it?
恶龙
Dragon.
是恶龙
Dragon!
那是条从北方飞来的恶龙
He was a Firedrake from the North.
史矛革来了
Smaug… had come!
那天就是一场屠杀
Such wanton death was dealt that day,
山下之城的防御对史矛革来说形同虚设
for this city of men was nothing to Smaug.
他的目光聚焦在别的地方
His eye was set on another price.
他对黄金有着黑暗而狂热的欲望
For dragons covet gold… with a dark and fierce desire.
攻击
Attack
不
No!
伊鲁柏…失守了
Erebor… was lost.
龙会守卫他的战利品直至死亡
For a dragon will guard his plunder as long as he lives.
快逃
Run for your lives!
帮帮我们
Help us!
瑟兰督伊不愿拿他的部属冒险 来对抗恶龙
Thrunduil would not risk the lives of his kin against the lawth of the dragon.
那天没有任何来自精灵的支援
No help came from the Elves that day.
后来也没有
Nor any day since.
家园被夺 伊鲁柏的矮人们四处游荡
Robbed of their homeland, the dwarves of Erebor wandered the wilderness.
曾经高高在上的人们也虎落平阳
The once mighty people brought low.
年轻的矮人王子在人类村落做工为生
The young dwarf prince took work where he could find it, laboring in the villages of men.
但他没有忘记
But always, he remembered…
月光下山上的浓烟 树木像火炬一样熊熊燃烧
the mountain smoke beneath the moon, the trees like torches blazing bright,
巨龙在空中喷火 城市在火焰中化为灰烬
where he had seen dragon fire in the sky, and a city turn to ash.
他永不会原谅 永不会遗忘
And he never forgave…and he never forgot.
亲爱的佛罗多 我就是这么出现的
That, my dear Frodo, is where I come in.
十分意外 因为一个巫师的意愿
For quite by chance, and the will of a wizard,
命运选中我成为这段故事的一部分
fate decided I would become part of this tale.
故事的开头 就像你预料的那样
It began… well, it began as you might expect.
在地底的洞穴里 居住着一个霍比特人
In a hole in the ground, there lived a hobbit.
这并不是一个又脏又湿 充满蠕虫和软泥味道的洞穴
Not a nasty, dirty wet hole full of worms and oozy smells.
这是一个霍比特人的家
This was a hobbit home.
这意味着这里有可口的食物 一个温暖的房子
And that means good food, a warm house…
一切在一个舒适的家里应有的东西
and all the comforts of home.
谢谢你
Thank you.
这是什么？
What's this?
不关你事 把你的脏爪子拿开
That is private. Keep your sticky paws off!
还没准备好
It's not ready yet.
什么还没准备好？
Not ready for what?
没准备好给人看
Reading.
这到底是什么？
What on earth are these?
派对邀请函的答复
Replies to the party invitations.
真够受欢迎的
Good gracious.
是今天么？
Is it today?
他们都说会来 除了萨克维尔·巴金斯
They all say they're coming, except for the Sackville-Bagginses,
他们希望你能亲自问他们
who're demanding you ask them in person.
真的么？等我死了再说
Are they, indeed. Over my dead body.
他们可能会觉得你说得对
They'd probably find that quite agreeable.
他们好像觉得你有数不清的财宝
They seem to think you have tunnels overflowing with gold.
只有一小箱子 离数不清差远了
It was one small chest, hardly overflowing.
还有着巨魔的恶臭
And it still smells of troll.
你到底在干嘛？
What on earth are you doing?
防患未然
Taking precautions!
有一次我抓到他们想偷走我的银饰
You know I caught them making off with the silverware once.
谁？
Who?
罗贝拉·萨克维尔·巴金斯
Lobelia Sackville-Baggins.
她的口袋里塞满了我的汤勺
She had all my spoons stuffed in her pockets.
可怕的女人
Dreadful woman.
在我…之后你要小心她
Make sure you keep an eye on her after I…
在我…
When I'm… when…
在你什么…？
When you're… what?
没什么 没什么
It's nothing… nothing.
有些人开始对你心存怀疑了
You know, some people are beginning to wonder about you.
他们觉得你越来越古怪了
They think you're becoming odd.
- 古怪？ - 唔
- odd? - Hmm…
不合群
Unsociable.
不合群？不可能
Unsociable, me? Nonsense.
行行好帮我把这个放门口去
Be a good lad and put that on the gate.
（非生日宴宾客不得入内）
你觉得他会来么？
Do you think he will come?
谁？
Who?
甘道夫
Gandalf.
他才不会放过任何一个放他的魔法烟火的机会
Oh, he wouldn't miss a chance to let off his wiz poppers.
他会给我们带来一次精彩表演的 等着吧
He'll give us quite a show, you'll see.
那就好 我走了
Right then. I am off.
去哪儿？
Off to where?
东郡森林 我要给他个惊喜
Eastfarthing woods. I'm going to surprise him.
去吧 不会迟到哟
Well go on then. You don't want to be late.
他可不喜欢迟到的人
He doesn't approve being late.
我也不喜欢
Not that I ever was.
那些日子里 我一直都很准时
In those days, I was always on time.
我多么可敬啊
I was entirely respectable…
也从未有过什么意料之外的事情发生
and nothing unexpected ever happened.
《意外之旅》
（60年前）
- 早上好 - 什么意思？
- Good morning. - What do you mean?
你的意思是 祝我早上好
Do you mean to wish me a good morning,
还是说 不管我想不想 这个早晨都不错？
or do you mean that it is a good morning whether I want it or not?
也许你只是想说 今天早上你感觉不错…
Or perhaps you mean to say that you feel good on this particular morning…
又或者你只是单纯地认为这会是个不错的早晨？
or are you simply stating that this is a morning to be good on?
我想可能是…上面的意思都有
All of them at once, I suppose.
有什么能帮助你的？
Can I help you?
这还有待观察
It remains to be seen.
我在找个人跟我一起去探险
I'm looking for someone to share in an adventure.
探险？
An adventure?
不 我想不到在布理西部…
No, I don't imagine anyone west of Bree…
谁会对探险有兴趣
who'd have much interest in adventures.
又脏又让人不安 还不怎么舒服
Nasty, disturbing… uncomfortable things.
吃饭都不能准点
Make you late for dinner!
早上好
Good morning!
你以为贝拉冬娜·图克的儿子一句早上好就能打发我
To think that I should have lived to be good-morninged by Belladonna Took's son,
就好像我是上门推销纽扣的
as if I was selling buttons at the door!
什么？
Beg your pardon?
你变了 而且并非都是朝好的方向变化 比尔博·巴金斯
You've changed, and not entirely for the better, Bilbo Baggins.
抱歉 我认识你么？
I'm sorry, do I know you?
虽然你没见过我 你可能知道我的名字
Would you know my name, although you don't remember I belong to it,
我是甘道夫
I'm Gandalf…
甘道夫的意思就是
and Gandalf means…
我
me!
甘道夫？那个放烟花的法师
Not Gandalf, the wandering wizard who made such excellent fireworks,
老图克仲夏夜请来的那个
Old Took used to have them on Midsummer's Eve!
我不知道你还在做这生意
I had no idea you were still in business.
不然我应该做什么？
And where else should I be?
好吧
Well…
好吧 很高兴你还记得一些关于我的事情
Well, I'm pleased to find you remember something about me…
虽然仅仅是我的烟花
even if it's only my fireworks.
就这么决定了
So that's decided.
这对你很有好处
It will be very good for you…
对我也很有趣 我会跟其他人说的
and most amusing for me. I shall inform the others.
跟谁… 不 等等
Inform the who-what-no, no. No, wait.
我们这儿不喜欢冒险 谢谢 今天不行
We do not want any adventures here, thank you-not today, not…
我建议你去山那边问问 或者河那边
I suggest you try over the hill or… across the water.
早上好
Good morning.
德瓦林
Dwalin…
乐意为您效劳
at your service.
比尔博·巴金斯
Bilbo… Baggins…
乐意为您效劳 不过我们认识么？
at yours. But do we know each other?
不
No.
走哪边 小伙子？
Which way, laddie?
是从这边下去么？
Is it down here?
下去哪儿？
Is- Is what? Down where?
晚餐 他说这里会有很多吃的
Supper. He said there'd be food. Lots of it.
他说？谁说的？
He- he said? Who said?
味道不错 还有么？
Very good dish. Any more?
什么？啊 有 有
What? Uh, oh, uh yes, yes.
请自便
Help yourself.
只是…
It's just that, hum…
我不知道会有人过来
I wasn't expecting company.
门铃响了
That would be the door.
巴林…乐意为您效劳
Balin… at your service.
晚上好
Good evening.
Yes, yes it is.
尽管我觉得晚点儿可能会下雨
Though I thing it might rain later.
我迟到了么？
Am I late?
迟到了什么？
Late… for what?
晚上好 兄弟
Evening, brother!
我的天
By my beard!
你比我上次见你的时候更心宽体胖了
You are shorter and wider than last we met.
胖了 但是没宽
Wider, not shorter.
我们俩都够机灵了
Sharp enough for both of us.
抱歉要打断你们一下
Excuse me. Sorry. I hate to interrupt.
但是我觉得你们可能走错房间了
Uh, but the thing is I'm not entirely sure you're in the right house.
你吃了么？
Have you eaten?
我并非不欢迎有客人来
It- It's not that I don't like visitors.
我和隔壁的霍比特人一样好客
I like visitors as much as the next hobbit.
但我希望在他们来拜访之前 我就认识他们了
But I do like to know them before they come… visiting…
- 这是什么？- 我不知道
- What's this? - I don't know,
我以为是奶酪呢
I just thought it a cheese,
- 问题是 - 都变蓝了
- The thing is… - Gone blue.
- 都是孔 但是它发霉了 - 现在的情况是
- It's riddled, but mold. - the thing is,
我不知道怎么开口 一点儿也不
I don't-I don't know how to begin. Not in the slightest.
恕我冒昧 但我必须说 我很抱歉
I don't mean to be blunt, but I- but I had to speak my mind. I'm sorry.
接受道歉
Apology accepted.
兄弟 倒满 别吝啬
Oh no, fill it up brother, don't stint.
我还能吃
I could eat again, if you insist.
- 菲力 - 还有奇力
- Fili. - and Kili.
乐意为您效劳
At your service.
你肯定就是巴金斯先生了
You most be Mr. Boggins.
不 别进来 你们肯定走错屋了
No! You can't come in, you've come to the wrong house.
你们…取消了么？
What's you- Has it been canceled?
没人跟我们说啊
No one told us.
不 没取消
Can- No, nothing's been canceled.
那就好
That's a relief.
小心点儿 我们刚磨好
Careful with these, we just had them sharpened.
这地方真不错
It's nice, this place.
你自己建的？
Did you do it yourself?
不是 这是祖传的
Well no, it's been in the family for years.
那是我妈妈的嫁妆盒 你能不这样做吗？
That's my mother's glory box, can you please not do that?
菲力 奇力 过来搭把手
Fili, Kili come on, give us a hand.
德瓦林先生
Mr. Dwalin.
我们挤挤 不然我们不可能都进来
Let's shove this in the hole, or otherwise we'll never get everyone in.
你们有多少人？
Everyone? How many more of you?
你想怎样？
What do you want?
不
Oh no.
不 不 家里没人
No, no. There's nobody home!
快走 去烦别人吧
Go away! And… bother somebody else.
我家里已经有太多矮人了
There's far too many dwarves in my dining room as it is.
如果这是哪个猪头在跟我开玩笑
If- if this is some… blunt head's idea of a joke,
我只能说 这真是无聊透顶
I can only say, it is in very… poor taste!
手拿开 笨蛋
Put your hands off, you big lump!
甘道夫
Gandalf.
这都是我的 抱歉 别碰我的酒
Those are my fr- Excuse me, not my wine!
放回去
Put that back.
Put that back!
果酱也不行 抱歉
Not the jam, please. Excuse me. Ex- Excuse me.
太多了吧 你有切奶酪的刀子么？
A tad excessive, isn't it? Have you got a cheese knife?
切奶酪的刀子？他整个都吃掉了
A cheese knife? He eats it by the block.
不不 那是蒙戈爷爷的椅子 不
No no, that's grandpa Mungo's chair, no-
就这样 放回去 拜托 放回去
ah, so is that. Take it back, please. Take it back,
这是古董 不是用来坐的 谢谢
this is antique, not for sitting on. Thank you.
那是书 不是杯托
That is a book, not a coaster.
把那地图放下
Uh, put that map down.
- 甘道夫先生 - 什么事？
- Excuse me, Mr. Gandalf. - Yes?
菊花茶要么？
May I tempt you with a cup of camomile?
谢谢你 朵力 我想我还是要点儿红酒吧
Ooh, no thank you Dori, a little red wine… for me I think.
菲力 奇力
Uh, Fili, Kili, uh…
欧音 格罗音 德瓦林 巴林
Oin, Gloin… Dwalin, Balin…
毕佛 波佛 庞博
Bifur, Bofur, Bombur…
- 多利 诺力 - 不 别
- Dori, Nori… - No, no,
别碰我的番茄 谢谢
not my dried tomatoes, thank you.
- 欧力 - 不 谢谢
- Ori! - No, thank you.
你是对的 毕佛
Yes you are quite right, Bifur.
我们好像还少一个人
We appear to be one dwarf short.
他迟到了
He is late, is all.
他去北方参加我们的一个家族会议 他会来的
He travel North to a meeting of our kin, he will come.
- 甘道夫先生 - 什么？
- Mr. Gandalf? - Hmm?
一杯红酒 有点儿果香
A little glass of red wine as requested, it's got a fruity bouquet.
干杯
Cheers.
- 巴林 - 抓住
- Balin… - Catch!
谁要麦芽酒？给你
Who wants an ale? There you go.
给
Here you go.
嘿 数到三
Hey, on the count of three!
一 二
One! Two!
快
Com'on!
抱歉 这是桌布 不是洗碗布
Ex- Excuse me, that is a doily, not a dish cloth.
但这上面都是洞
But it's full of holes!
它本来就是那样的 那是针织的
It's supposed to look like that, it's crochet.
如果你有个球的话 会很好玩
Oh, and a wonderful game it is too, if you got the balls for it.
这些惹祸的烦人的矮人
Bebother and confusticate these dwarves!
亲爱的比尔博 到底怎么了？
My dear Bilbo, what on earth is the matter?
怎么了？
What's the matter?
我周围都是矮人 他们来这儿干嘛？
I am surrounded by dwarves. What they're doing here?
等你习惯了他们 这会是个快乐的聚会
Oh, they're quite a merry gathering… once you get used to 'em.
我不想习惯
I don't want to get used to them.
看看我的厨房 地毯上都是泥
Look at the state of my kitchen! There's mud trodding the carpet,
我的储藏室像被洗劫了一样
they- they've pillaged the pantry,
我还没跟你说他们在浴室里做了什么
I'm not even gonna tell you what they've done in the bathroom,
他们把水管搞得一塌糊涂
they've all but destroyed the plumbing!
我不知道他们在我屋里做什么
I don't understand what they're doing in my house!
很抱歉打断你
Excuse me, I'm sorry to interrupt.
我应该把盘子放哪儿？
But what sha'd do with my plate?
来 欧力 给我吧
Here you go, Ori, give it to me.
喂
Excuse me!
那是我妈妈的藏品 已经有一百多年历史了
That's my mother's Westfarthing pottery, it's over a hundred years old!
你们能不能别这样？你们会把它们弄钝的
And- and ca- can you not do that, you'll blunt them!
你们听到了么？
Ooh, d'you hear that, lads?
他说我们会把刀子弄钝的
He says we'll blunt the knives!
∮ 刀子弄钝 叉子弄弯 ∮
∮ Blunt the knives, bend the forks ∮
∮ 瓶子弄碎 木头烧完 ∮
∮ Smash the bottles and burn the corks ∮
∮ 瓶子打破 盘子打烂 ∮
∮ Chip the glasses and crack the plates ∮
∮ 这些事情让比尔博·巴金斯生厌 ∮
∮ That's what Bilbo Baggins hates ∮
∮ 剪破衣服 踩烂黄油 ∮
∮ Cut the cloth and tread on the fat ∮
∮ 剩下骨头留在卧室 ∮
∮ Leave the bones on the bedroom-mat ∮
∮ 牛奶倒进储物室 ∮
∮ Pour the milk on the pantry-floor ∮
∮ 红酒洒上每扇门 ∮
∮ Splash the wine on every door ∮
∮ 瓦罐倒进沸腾的碗 ∮
∮ Dump the crocks in a boiling bowl ∮
∮ 再用大棒把它打烂 ∮
∮ Pound them up with a thumping pole ∮
∮ 当你结束还有完卵 ∮
∮ When you've finished, if any are whole ∮
∮ 大厅一扔保准完蛋 ∮
∮ Send them down the hall to roll! ∮
∮ 这些事情让比尔博·巴金斯生厌
∮ That's what Bilbo Baggins hates! ∮
他来了
He's here.
甘道夫
Gandalf.
你不是说这地方很好找么？
I thought you said this place would be easy to find.
我都迷路两次了
I lost my way, twice.
要不是门上有记号 我根本找不到
I wouldn't have found it at all, had it not been for that mark on the door.
记号？门上没记号 一周前才粉刷过
Mark? There's no mark on that door, it was painted a week ago!
有的 这是我亲手做的手脚
There is a mark, I have put it there myself.
比尔博·巴金斯 请允许我向你介绍我们的领头人
Bilbo Baggins, allow me to introduce the leader of our company,
索林·橡木盾
Thorin Oakenshield.
那么说…
So…
这就是那个霍比特人了
This is the hobbit.
跟我说说 巴金斯先生 你打过架么？
Tell me Mr. Baggins, have you done much fighting?
什么？
Pardon me?
斧头还是剑？你一般用什么武器？
Axe or sword, what's your weapon of choice?
如果非要说的话 我板栗游戏玩得不错
Well, I do have some skill at conkers, if you must know.
但我不觉得这有什么用
But I fail to see… why that's relevant.
我猜到了
I thought as much.
他怎么看都像个杂货商 而不是飞贼
He looks more like a grocer than a burglar.
伊瑞德隆会议有什么消息？
What news from the meeting in Ered Luin?
他们都来么？
Did they all come?
是的
Aye,
七个国家的使者
envoys from all seven kingdoms.
铁丘陵矮人怎么说？
And what did the dwarvesof the Iron Hill say?
达因会一起来么？
Is Dain with us?
他们不会
They will not come.
他们说这只是我们的探险
They say this quest is ours, and ours alone.
你们要探险？
You're doing a quest?
比尔博 把灯调亮点儿
Bilbo, my dear fellow, let us have a little more light.
一路向东
Far to the East,
越过山岭和河流
over ranges and rivers,
夸过森林和荒地
beyond woodlands and wastelands,
有一座孤独的山峰
lies a single solitary peak.
孤山
The Lonely Mountain.
是的 欧音已经看过预言 预言说：是时候了
Aye, Oin has read the portents, and the portents say: it is time.
有人看到乌鸦像预言中说的那样飞回山里
Ravens have been seen flying back to the mountain as it was foretold.
当前朝的鸟飞回伊鲁柏时
When the birds of the old return to Erebor,
野兽的统治就到头了
the reign of the beast will end.
什么野兽？
what beast?
那可能是指可怕的史矛革
Well that would be a reference to Smaug the terrible,
我们那个时代最大的灾难
chiefest and greatest calamity of our age.
喷火的鼻息
Airborne fire breather…
剃刀一样的牙齿 肉钩一样的爪子
teeth like razors, claws like meat hooks,
极度热爱黄金
extremely fond of precious metals.
我知道龙是什么样子
Yes, I know what a dragon is.
我不怕 我等着它
I'm not afraid, I'm up for it.
我要让他的屁股尝尝矮人兵器的味道
I'll give him a taste of the dwarfish iron right up his jacksy!
左下
Sit down.
就算是有一支军队 这个探险也很难完成
The task would be difficult enough with an army behind us.
何况我们只有十三个人
but we number just thirteen…
还不是最好最聪明的十三个人
and not thirteen of the best nor brightest.
你说谁蠢呢？
Hey! Who you're calling dimp!
我们虽然人数少
We may be few in number.
但我们都是战士
But we're fighters…
我们都是 战斗到最后一人
all of us! To the last one!
你们忘了我们还有一个巫师同行么？
And you forget we have a wizard in our company,
甘道夫他一生中已经杀了数百头龙
Gandalf, who have killed hundreds of dragons in his time.
没有 我没那么说过
Oh, well no, uh, I- I wouldn't say-
那是多少？
How many then?
什么？
What?
你杀死了多少头龙？
Well, how many dragons have you killed?
快说 把数字告诉我们
Go on, give us a number!
拜托 拜托…
Uh… Give me- Please, please.
够了
Enough!
既然我们能看到这些征兆 难道别人就看不到么？
If we have read these signs, do you not think others will have read them too?
已经谣言四起了
Rumors have begun to spread.
巨龙史矛革已经六十年未现身了
The dragon Smaug has not been seen for 60 years.
许多目光望着东方 估摸… 思索…
Eyes look East to the mountain, assessing… wondering…
权衡风险
weighing the risk.
或许我们的巨大财富现在正无人看守 我们要坐等…
Perhaps the vast wealth of our people now lies unprotected. Do we sit back…
其他人占有我们的财富么？
while others claim what is rightfully ours?
还是我们要把握机会夺回伊鲁柏？
Or do we seize this chance to take back Erebor?!
你忘了前门被封死了么？
You forget the front gate is sealed.
没有进山的路了
There is no way into the mountain.
亲爱的巴林 那不是真的
That, my dear Balin, is not totally true.
你凭什么？
How came you by this?
这是你父亲索恩托我保管的
It was given to me by your father… by Thrain… for safekeeping.
现在是你的了
It is yours now.
如果这是把钥匙的话…那肯定有一扇门
If there is a key… there must be a door!
这上面说有一条秘道通向底层大厅
These runes speak of a hidden passage to the lower halls.
有别的路进去？
There's another way in?
就算我们能找到它 但是矮人的大门在锁着时都是隐形的
Well, if we can find it, but dwarf doors are invisible when closed.
答案就在这张地图上
The answer lies hidden somewhere in this map,
我没办法找到 但是…
and I do not have the skill to find it, but…
中土之地有人能
there are others in Middle-earth who can.
我心里的计划需要很多的秘密行动
The task I have in mind will require a great deal of stealth,
也不能缺乏勇气
and no small amount of courage.
但是如果我们够谨慎又够聪明 我相信我们就能成功
But if we're careful and clever, I believe that it can be done.
那就是我们为什么需要一个飞贼
That's why we need a burglar.
要我说 需要一个好手 一个专家
Hmm. And a good one too. An expert, I would imagine.
你是么？
And are you?
我是什么？
Am I what?
他说他是个专家
He said he's an expert!
我？不不不 我不是飞贼
Me? No. No no no no. I- I'm not a burglar.
我一辈子都没偷过东西
I've never stolen anything in my life.
恐怕我不得不同意巴金斯先生说的
And I'm afraid I have to agree with Mr. Baggins.
他根本不是飞贼的料
He's hardly burglar material.
对 荒野可不是无法照顾自己的人能生活的地方
Aye, the wild is no place for gentle folk who can neither fight nor fend for themselves.
够了 我说巴金斯是一个飞贼 他就是一个飞贼
Enough! If I say Bilbo Baggins is a burglar, then a burglar he is.
霍比特人脚步灵敏
Hobbits are remarkably light on their feet.
事实上 他们可以通过任何地方而不被发现
In fact, they can pass unseen by most if they choose…
而且巨龙已经习惯了矮人的味道
and while the dragon is accustomed to the smell of a dwarf,
但他对霍比特人一无所知
the scent of a hobbit is all about unknown to him,
这对我们来说是个优势
which gives us a distinct advantage.
你们让我找团队中的第十四个人
You asked me to find the 14th member of this company,
我选中了巴金斯先生
and I have chosen Mr. Baggins.
他可是深藏不露
There's a lot more into him than his appearances suggest.
他能贡献的比你们想象中的要多
And he's got a great deal more to offer than any of you know…
甚至他自己都不知道
including himself.
这一点你们必须相信我
You must trust me on this.
好吧
Very well…
就听你的
We'll do it your way.
不 不
No. No
把契约给他
Give him your contract.
- 我们加入 - 拜托
- We're in. - Please.
我们准备好了
We're off!
这只是最普通的契约 关于费用
It's just the usual: summary about the pocket expenses…
所需时间 酬劳和葬礼安排等事项的说明
time required, remuneration, funeral arrangements, so forth.
葬礼安排？
Funeral arrangements?
我们不能保证他的安全
We cannot guarantee his safety.
明白了
Understood.
我们不会对他的命运负责
We will not be responsible for his fate.
同意
Agreed.
「全部现金付款 金额最高不超过…
"…total's cash on delivery up to but not exceeding…
所有获益的十四分之一「 看起来挺公平
one fourteenth of total profit if any". Seems fair.
现有的团队不会对由持续伤害造成的伤残负责
"The present company shall not be liable for injuries inflicted by or sustained
包括但不限于…
as a consequence thereof, including, but not limited to…
撕裂
lacerations…
挖脏？
evisceration?
烧死？
Incineration?
是的 他一眨眼就会把你的血肉熔化
Oh, aye, he'll melt the flesh off your bones in the blink of an eye.
你还好么 小伙子？
You alright, laddie?
是的 我…
Huh? Yeah, I fe-
有点儿头晕
Feel a bit faint.
把它想象成会飞的火炉就好
Think furnace, with wings.
我需要点空气
Hey, I-I-I need air.
火光闪过 烧灼的疼痛过后 嘭一声
Flash of light, searing pain, and puf!
你就变成一撮灰烬了
You're nothing more than a pile of ash!
不
No-
真会安慰人 毕佛
Oh, very helpful, Bifur.
我没事儿 就让我安静坐会儿就好
I'll be alright. Just… let me… sit quietly for a moment.
你已经坐了够久了
You've been sitting quietly for far too long.
告诉我
Tell me…
从什么时候开始
When did doilies…
这些小饰物和你妈妈的盘子对你来说这么重要了
and your mother's dishes become so important to you?
我记得那个在树林四处找寻精灵的小霍比特人
I remember a young hobbit who was always running off in search of Elves, in woods.
他会在外面待到很晚
He would stay out late.
天黑后 带着泥巴 树枝和萤火虫回家
Come home, after dark, trailing mud and twigs and fireflies.
一个喜欢探索
A young hobbit who would've liked nothing better than to find out
夏尔之外的世界的小霍比特人
what was beyond the borders of the Shire.
世界并不存在于你的书和地图上
The world is not in your books and maps.
而是在外面
It's out there.
我不能就这么跑出去探险
I can't just go running off into the blue.
我是巴金斯家的乡巴佬
I am a Baggins… of Bagg End.
你也是一个图克家的人
You are also a Took.
你知道你的曾曾曾曾祖叔吼牛·图克
Did you know that your great great great great uncle, Bullroarer Took,
他体型巨大 可以骑一匹真正的马
was so large, he could ride a real horse?
是的 他能
Yes, well he could!
在绿野战役 他加入讨伐哥布林的大军
In the battle of Greenfields, he charged the Goblin ranks
挥舞着大棒 抡飞了哥布林国王的脑袋
he swung his club so hard, it knocked the Goblin king's head clean off,
那头颅飞起几百码 最后滚到兔子洞里
and it sailed a hundred yards through the air, and went down a rabbit hole.
这场战役就此取得了胜利
And thus the battle as won…
从此还发明了高尔夫球
and the game of golf invented at the same times.
我觉得这是你瞎编的
I do believe you made that up.
所有的好故事都需要这样的修饰
Well, all good stories deserve embellishment.
你回来以后 也会有一两个自己的故事
You'll have a tale or two to tell of your own when you come back.
你能保证我能回来么？
Can you promise that I will come back?
不能
No…
但如果你能回来
And if you do…
你会变得很不一样
you'll not be the same.
我同意
That's what I thought.
对不起 我不能签这合同
Sorry, Gandalf, I can't sign this.
你找错人了
You've got the wrong hobbit.
我们似乎失去了我们的飞贼
It appears we have lost our burglar.
也许是最好的那个
Probably for the best.
运气总是不站在我们这一边
The odds were always against us.
看看我们都是些什么人
After all, what are we?
商人 矿工
Merchants, minors…
锅炉匠 玩具工
tinkers, toy makers.
都不是成为传奇的料
Hardly the stuff of legend.
仅有的几个战士
There are a few warriors amongst us.
都是老战士
Old warriors.
我会带着这里的每一个矮人统率铁丘陵军队
I would take each and every one of these dwarves over an army from the Iron Hills…
因为每当我召唤他们 他们就会响应
for when I called upon them, they answered.
忠诚
Loyalty…
荣誉
Honor…
热忱
A willing heart…
除此以外 我别无所求
I can ask no more than that.
你没必要做这些的
You don't have to do this.
你可以选择
You have a choice.
你已经让我们感到自豪了
You've done honorably by our people.
你已经在蓝山为我们开创了新生活
You have bulit a new life for us in the Blue Mountains…
太平富裕的生活
a life of peace and plenty.
比伊鲁柏所有的黄金更珍贵的生活
A life that is worth more than all the gold in Erebor.
这个责任从爷爷传给了我父亲 现在又落到了我手上
From my grandfather to my father, this has come to me.
他们做梦都想伊鲁柏的矮人们能够夺回故土
They dreamt of the day when the dwarves of Erebor would reclaim their homeland.
这没有选择 巴林
There is no choice, Balin.
对我来说也是
Not for me.
那我们就和你一起战斗
Then we are with you, laddie.
这个梦想会实现的
We will see it done.
∮ 从远方寒冷的高山 ∮
∮ Far over the misty mountains cold ∮
∮ 来到幽深古老的窑洞 ∮
∮ To dungeons deep and caverns old ∮
∮ 我们必须在破晓之前出发 ∮
∮ We must away ere break of day ∮
∮ 去寻找久已遗忘的财富 ∮
∮ To find our long forgotten gold ∮
∮ 松树在高山上摇摆 ∮
∮ The pines were roaring on the height ∮
∮ 高风在夜空中呜咽 ∮
∮ The winds were moaning in the night ∮
∮ 熊熊烈火 火焰蔓延 ∮
∮ The fire was red, it flaming spread ∮
∮ 树木如炬 熠熠闪光 ∮
∮ The trees like torches blazed with light ∮
有人吗？
Hello!
比尔博 有什么追你么？
Hey! Mr. Bilbo. Where're you after?
我不能停 我已经迟到了
I can't stop, I'm already late!
迟到什么？
Late for what?
我要去探险
I'm going on an adventure!
等等
Wait!
等等我
我已经签了
I signed it.
一切都很顺利
Everything appears to be in order.
巴金斯大人 欢迎你…
Welcome, master Baggins…
加入索林·橡木盾的队伍
in the company of Thorin Oakenshield.
给他一匹马
Give him a pony.
不 不 不 没那必要
No, no no no. That- that won't be necessary.
我肯定我走着能跟得上
I can- I am sure I can keep up on foot,
我经常步行散步
yeah, I- I've done my fair share of… walking holidays, you know,
最远还去过蛙山
even got as far as the Frog Mountain once-
快点诺力 付钱
Come on Nori. pay up!
还有一个
One more.
怎么回事？
What's that about?
他们打赌 赌你会不会出现
Oh they took wagers…on whether or not you would turn up.
大多数人赌你不会来
Most of them bet that you wouldn't.
你呢？
And what did you think?
我亲爱的朋友 我从没怀疑过你
My dear fellow…I never doubted of you for a second.
啊 是马毛
Oh it's horsehair.
过敏了
Having a reaction.
等等 停下来
Wait, wait. Stop!
停下来 我们得掉头
Stop! We have to turn around.
到底怎么了
What in earth is the matter?
我忘记带手帕了
I forgot my handkerchief.
来
Here!
用这个吧
Use this.
继续出发
Move on!
你必须习惯没有手帕的情况
You'll have to manage without pocket handkerchiefs,
还有很多其他事情 比尔博·巴金斯
and a good many other things, Bilbo Baggins,
直到我们旅程结束
before we reach our journey's end.
你生于夏尔的延绵山岭和小河旁
You were born to the rolling hills and little rivers of the Shire.
但是现在家已在身后
But home is now behind you.
而世界在前方
The world is ahead.
好家伙 真是个好家伙
Good girl! Here's a good girl.
这是我们俩的小秘密 香桃儿
It's our little secret, Myrtle,
谁也别告诉 嘘 嘘…
Just tell no one, shh shh…
那是什么东西？
What was that?
半兽人
Orcs.
半兽人？
Orcs?
杀人魔
Throat cutters.
大概有几十个
There'd be dozens of them out there.
那边的低洼地里都是
The low lands are crawling with them.
凌晨大家都熟睡的时候 他们就发动袭击
They strike, in the wee small hours, when everyone's asleep.
又快又静 没有尖叫声 只有血流遍地
Quick and quiet, no screams. Just lots of blood.
你们觉得很有趣？
You think that's funny?
你们觉得被半兽人夜袭是有趣的事情？
You think a night raid by orcs is a joke?
我们不是这个意思
We didn't mean anything by it.
当然不是
No you didn't.
你们对这个世界根本一无所知
You know nothing of the world.
别介意 小伙子
Don't mind him, laddie.
索林比大多数人更加仇恨半兽人是有原因的
Thorin has more cause than most to hate orcs.
恶龙占领了孤寂山后
After the dragon took the Lonely Mountain,
索尔国王设法收回古矮人族的摩瑞亚王国
King Thror tried to reclaim the ancient dwarf kingdom of Moria.
但是我们的敌人已经先到一步
But our enemy had got' there first.
摩瑞亚已经被半兽人大军占领
Moria had been taken by legions of orcs,
首领则是他们种族里最卑鄙的…
led by the most vile of all their race…
阿索格… 毁灭者
Azog… the Defiler.
刚达巴山的半兽人已经宣誓
The giant Gundabad orc had sworn
要彻底摧毁杜林的防线
to wipe out the line of Durin.
他从把国王斩首开始
He began by beheading the king.
不…
Noooo!
索恩 就是索林的父亲 因悲痛过度而疯了
Thrain, Thorin's father, was driven mad by grief,
他是失踪了 被俘虏 还是被杀 我们不得而知
he went missing, taken prisoner or killed, we did not know.
我们群龙无首
We were leaderless.
溃败和死亡笼罩着我们…
Defeat and death were upon us.
而就在那时…我看到了他
That is when… I saw him.
一位年轻的矮人国王子降伏了这个白半兽人
A young dwarf prince facing down the Pale Orc.
他独自抗击这个可怕的敌人
He stood alone against this terrible foe.
他的盔甲破了 没有武器 只有一根橡木枝做的盾牌
His armor rent, wielding nothing but an oaken branch as a shield.
毁灭者阿索格那天意识到
Azog the Defiler learned that day,
杜林的防线没有那么容易被击破
that the line of Durin would not be so easily broken.
我们重整队伍 把半兽人击退回去
Our forces rallied, and drove the orcs back.
敌人被我们打败了
Our enemy had been defeated…
但那天晚上没有庆功宴 也没有胜利的歌声
but there was no feast, nor song that night…
因为我们伤亡惨重 我们极度悲痛
for our dead were beyond the count of grief.
只有很少人幸存了下来
We few, had survived…
那时候我就在想
and I thought to myself then…
还有一个人…我可以追随
there is one… who I could follow…
有这样一个人…
there is one…
我可以称他为王
I could call king.
那个白半兽人呢？
And the Pale Orc?
他后来怎样了？
What happened to him?
他溜回了他的城堡
He slunk back into the hall whence he came.
那个肮脏的家伙很久之前就因伤而亡了
That filth died of his wounds long ago.
告诉主人
我们发现矮人了
我说 甘道夫先生？
There. Mr. Gandalf?
你就不能对这大雨施点魔法吗？
Can't you do something about this deluge?
这是在下雨 矮人大人
It is raining, master dwarf.
结束一场雨最好的办法 就是让雨下完
And it will continue to rain until the rain is done!
如果你想改变这个世界的天气
If you wish to change the weather of the world,
你应该找别的巫师
you should find yourself another wizard.
有吗？
Are there any?
什么？
What?
别的巫师？
Other wizards?
巫师一共有五个
There are five of us.
最厉害的是白袍巫师萨鲁曼
The greatest of our order is Saruman. The White.
然后有两个蓝袍巫师
Then there are the two blue wizards…
我几乎忘记他们的名字了
D'you know, I have quite forgotten their names.
那第五个是谁？
And who is the fifth?
那是褐袍巫师瑞达加斯特
Well, that would be Radagast. The Brown.
他是很厉害的巫师还是跟你一样？
Is he a great wizard or is he more like you?
我觉得他是个非常厉害的巫师 就他的领域而言
I think he's a very great wizard… in his own way.
他性格温和 喜欢和动物待在一起
He's a gentle soul who prefers the company of animals to others.
他密切关注着东方的广阔林地
He keeps a watchful eye over the vast forestlands to the East,
也是件好事 因为邪恶总是在这个世界上寻找立足之地
and a good thing too, for always evil will look to find a foothold in this world.
不好
Not good…
一点都不好
Not good at all!
噢 不要
Oh no…
塞巴斯蒂安
Sebastian!
天啊
Good gracious.
闪开 让他好好呼吸 拜托
Move back, give him some air, for goodness sake!
我不明白为什么不起作用
I don't understand why it's not working,
怎么不像是巫术
it's not as if it's witchcraft.
巫术…
Witchcraft…
哦…
Oh…
是巫术
But it is!
黑暗而强大的
A dark and powerful…
巫术
magic.
这些邪恶的东西到底从哪儿来的？
Where on this good earth do those foul creatures come from?
古堡那儿？
The old fortress?
带我去
Show me.
今晚我们在这里扎营
We camp here for the night.
菲力 奇力 看好马
Fili, Kili, look after the ponies.
确保它们跟你们待在一块
Make sure you stay with them.
有个农民和他家人曾住在这儿
A farmer and his family used to live here.
欧音 葛罗音
Oin, Gloin.
诶？
Aye?
生起火来
Get the fire going.
我觉得继续前进更加明智
I think it would be wiser to move on.
我们能赶到藏身谷
We could make for the hidden valley.
但我已经告诉过你
But I've told you already.
我不会靠近那个地方
I will not go near that place.
为什么？
Why not?
精灵族可以帮我们 我们可以获得食物 休息和建议
The Elves could help us, we could get food, rest, advice.
我不需要他们的建议
I don't need their advice.
我们有张看不懂的地图 爱隆国王可以帮助我们
We have a map that we cannot read. Lord Elrond could help us.
帮助？
Help?
恶龙袭击伊鲁柏时 精灵族的帮助在哪儿？
A dragon attacks Erebor. What help came from the Elves?
半兽人侵略摩瑞亚 玷污我们的圣堂
Orcs plunder Moria, desecrate our sacred halls,
精灵族在那里袖手旁观
the Elves looked on and did nothing!
你居然让我去找那群背叛我祖父
You ask me to seek out the very people who betrayed my grandfather…
背叛我父亲的人
who betrayed my father.
但你不是你的祖辈
You are neither of them.
我给你地图和钥匙可不是为了让你纠结于过去
I did not give you that map and key for you to hold on to the past.
我不认为那些该由你保管
I did not know they were yours to keep.
没事吧？
Everything alright?
甘道夫 你要去哪儿？
Gandalf, where are you going?
去找这里唯一还有理智的人
To seek the company of the only one around here who's got any sense.
谁？
And who's that?
我自己 巴金斯先生
Myself, mister Baggins!
我受够矮人的气了
I've had enough of dwarves for one day.
赶紧 庞博 都饿了
Come on Bumbur, we're hungry.
他还会回来吗？
Is he coming back?
离开这么久了
It's been a long time.
谁？
Who?
甘道夫
Gandalf.
他可是个巫师 他想怎样就怎样
He's a wizard! He does as he chooses.
来 搭把手 给端过去
Here. Do us a favor, take this to the lads.
别吃了 你已经吃得够多了
Stop it, you've had plenty.
怎么了？
What's the matter?
我们应该看守马儿的
We're supposed to be looking after the ponies.
只是我们遇到了一个小问题
Only we've encountered a…slight problem.
我们有16匹马
We had sixteen.
现在只有14匹
Now there's… fourteen.
黛茜和邦戈不见了
Daisy and Bungle are missing.
什么？
What?
那可不是好事 真的不是好事
Well, that's… not good, and that is not good at all.
我们是不是该告诉索林？
Shouldn't we tell Thorin?
不要 还是不要打扰他了
Eh, no. Let's not worry him.
作为我们当中的职业大盗 我们觉得你应该想追查到底
As our official burglar, we thought you might like to look into it.
那个 呃…
Well, eh…
看起来好像有大家伙把这些树连根拔起了
it looks as if something big uprooted these trees.
我们也是这么想的
That was our thinking.
是个很大的家伙 而且也许很危险
It's something very big, and possibly quite dangerous.
那边有光
Hey! There's a light.
走这边
Move here.
蹲下
Stay down.
那是什么？
What is it?
山怪
Trolls.
他抓了小香桃和小薄荷
He's got Myrtle and Minty!
我想他们要抓去吃了 我们应该做点什么
I think they're gonna eat them, we have to do something.
没错 你应该做点什么
Yes, you should.
山怪们又慢又笨
Mountain trolls are slow and stupid,
- 而你身材苗条 - 我？不行
- and you're so small, - Me? Me, no.
他们看不到你 绝对安全
they'll never see you. It's perfectly safe!
我们就跟你后边
We'll be right behind you.
如果你遇到麻烦 就学谷仓猫头鹰叫两声 棕色猫头鹰叫一声
If you run into trouble hoot twice like a barn owl, once like a brown owl.
学谷仓猫头鹰叫两声 学棕色…叫…
Twice like a barn owl, hoot twice like a… brown, hoots like a-
你确定这是个好主意？
like a- ah, are you sure this is a good idea?
昨天吃羊肉 今天吃羊
Mutton yesterday, mutton today, and blimey,
不会明天还吃羊吧
if it don't look like mutton again tomorrer.
你的眼睛看哪里了？这不是羊
What yer would be? These ain't sheep!
这是野马
These is waste nags!
- 哦不 马？ - 我不喜欢马肉
- Oh no, horse? - I don't like horse.
从来不喜欢 一点肥肉都没有
I never have. Not enough fat on them.
不过也比那个难嚼的老农好 他只有皮和骨头
Well, it's bett'r of a leathery ol' farmer. Only skin and bone he was.
到现在还要让我剔牙
I'm still pickin' bits of him out o' me teeth.
好可爱 鼻涕变油花儿了
Well, that's lovely, that is. A floater.
也许能调调味
Oh! Might improve the flavor!
那我多弄点儿出来
Oh! Heve more where that came from.
别动
Oh no yer don't!
坐下
Sit down!
好吧…
Well…
能不能把鼻涕捞出来啊？
Oh I hope yer gonna gut these nags?
我可不喜欢那块臭不拉叽的
I don't like the stinky parts.
我让你坐下
I said sit down!
我饿死了 今晚我们吃马肉还是怎么着？
I'm starving, are we having horse tonight or what?
闭上你的臭嘴 给你啥你就吃啥
Shut yer cake hole, you'll eat what I pig ya.
为什么他是厨子？什么东西都做成一个味道
How come he's the cook? Ev'rything tastes the same,
什么东西都吃起来像鸡肉
ev'rything tastes like chicken,
除了鸡肉以外
except the chicken,
鸡肉吃起来像鱼
what tastes like fish!
我说过了 要心存感激多说好话
I'm just saying, a little appreciation would be nice.
「非常感谢 伯特 」
"Thank you very much, Bert."
「非常棒的汤 伯特」 有那么难吗？
"Lovely stew, Bert." How hard is that?
再加点松鼠便便就行了
Just needs a sprinkle o' squirrel dung.
嘿 那是我的烈酒
Hey, that's my grog!
不好意思
Sorry.
真是精准的调味 真是…
Ooh. That is beautifully balanced, that is…
把你屁股挪开 老兄
Wrap yer loganbie around that, mate.
不错吧？
Huh? Good ain't it?
所以我才是厨子
That's why I'm the cook.
我肚子乱叫了 我要吃点垫垫肚子
Me guts are rambling. I've got to snack on something.
肉 我要吃肉
Flesh. I need flesh!
天哪
Blimey!
伯特 看我鼻子里擤出什么来啦
Burt! Burt, look what's come out o' me hooter!
他还有胳膊有腿的
He's got arms and legs and ev'ryting!
他是什么人种？
What is he?
我不知道 可我不喜欢他扭来扭去的样子
I don't know, but I don't like the way he wriggles around!
你是什么东西？大松鼠吗？
What are yer then? An oversized squirrel?
我是个飞贼 呃 霍比特人
I'm a burglar-uh, hobbit!
「飞贼霍比特人」？
A "burglarhobit"?
能把他煮了吃吗？
Can we cook him?
试试看
We can try!
去了皮和骨头之后 他还不够我吃一口
He wouldn't make more than a mouthful. Not when he's skinned and boned!
也许附近还有更多的飞贼霍比特人
P'raps there's more burglarhobits 'round these parts,
够用来做个馅儿饼了
might be enough for a pie!
逮住他 他太快了
Grab him! He's too quick!
啊 过来 小可爱
Oah, come here, you little…
抓住了
Gotcha!
还有别的小伙伴藏在你刚才那儿吗？
Are there any more of you little fellas hiding where you shouldn't?
没有
No.
他在撒谎
He's lying!
我没撒谎
I'm not!
拎着他的脚趾头烤烤火
Hold his toes over the fire.
让他叫唤叫唤
Make him squeal!
放下他
Drop him!
你干嘛？
You what?
我说…
I said…
放下他
drop him.
- 比尔博 - 不
- Bilbo! - No!
放下武器
Lay down your arms!
不然就把他撕了
Or we'll whip his off!
怎么煮他们不用愁
Don't bother cooking 'em!
最好直接坐上去把他们压成肉酱
Best to sit on 'em, and… squash 'em into jelly!
应该先腌一下 然后撒上鼠尾草烤了吃
They should be so salted and grilled with a sprinkle of sage.
有必要这样吗？
Is this really necessary?
听起来确实不错
That does sound quite nice.
别介意调料了 已经过了大半夜了
Never mind the seas'ning, we ain't got all night!
马上就要黎明了 我们快点弄
Dawn ain't far away, let's get a move on!
我可不想被变成石头
I don't fancy been turned to stone.
等等
Wait!
你们犯大错了
You are making a terrible mistake.
跟他们讲道理是没用的 他们是弱智
You can't reason with them, they're half-wits!
弱智？那我们成什么了？
Half-wits? What does that make us?
我意思是 在烹饪的方面
I meant with the, uh, with the- with the seasoning.
什么烹饪的方面？
What… about the seasoning?
你闻过他们吗？
Well, have you smelt them?
把他们端上盘子前 你需要用比鼠尾草更多的料
You're gonna need something stronger than sage before you plate this lot up!
叛徒
Traitor!
你知道怎么煮矮人？
What do you know about cooking dwarf?
闭嘴 让这个飞贼霍比特人讲
Shut up, and let the, uh, flurgerburburhobit talk.
煮矮人的秘诀就是…
Uh, the-the secret to cooking dwarf, is umm…
怎么做？
Yes?
快说
Come on,
- 就是… - 告诉我们秘诀
- It's, uh, - tell us the secret?
准确地说 秘诀就是…
Ye- yes, the damn thing is- the secret is…
先剥皮
to… skin them first!
汤姆 给我切片刀
Tom, get me filleting knife.
过来 我要捆了你…
Come, I'll get you, you little-
我会报仇的…
I won't forget that, I won't forget t-
蠢话
What a load of rubbish!
我都带着皮吃了好多了
I've eaten plenty with their skins on.
都是狼吞虎咽 连着鞋
Scoff 'em I say, boots and all!
他说得对
He's right!
生吃矮人又怎么样呢
Nothing wrong with a bit o' raw dwarf.
味道好 嘎吱脆
Nice and crunchy.
不要吃那个 他有传染病
Uh no, not-not that one, he's infected!
你说啥？
You what?
他有寄生虫在肚子里
Yeah he's got worms in his tubes.
实际上 他们的身体里都有很多寄生虫
In- in fact, they all have. They're infested with parasites,
非常糟糕 我的话就不会冒险 真的不会
it's a terrible business, I wouldn't risk it, I really wouldn't.
寄生虫？他说的是寄生虫吗？
Parasite, did he say parasite?
可我们没寄生虫啊
But we don't have parasites!
你有寄生虫
You have parasites.
我有像我胳膊这么大的寄生虫
I've got parasites as big as my arm!
我的最大 我有超级大的寄生虫
Mine are the biggest parasites, I've got huge parasites!
我们全身都是
We're riddled!
对 全身都是
Yes, all riddled!
大坨大坨的寄生虫
Yes we are, badly!
那你让我们怎么办？
What would you have us do then?
全放他们走？
Let 'em all go?
呃…
Well…
你以为我不知道你在搞什么鬼吗？
You think I don't know what you're up to.
这个小狐狸…拿我们当白痴呢
This little ferret… is taking us for fools!
小狐狸？
Ferret?
白痴？
Fools?
黎明之光将收服你们
The dawn will take you all!
- 那是谁？ - 不晓得
- Who's that? - No idea.
我们能把他一块吃了吗？
Can we eat him too?
把你的脚从我背上拿开
Ooh, get your foot out of my back!
可否问一下 你去哪儿了？
Where did you go to, if I may ask?
看看前面的情况
To look ahead.
为什么又回来了？
What brought you back?
看看后面的情况
Looking behind.
不是件好事情
Nasty business.
至少他们还没被撕烂
Still they all are in one piece.
该谢谢你的飞贼朋友
No thanks to your burglar.
他在拖延时间
He had the nose to play for time.
你们都没想到这个点子
None of the rest of you thought of that.
他们一定是从伊顿荒原上下来的
They must have come down from the Ettenmoors.
这些山怪什么时候开始向南方走这么远了？
Since when the mountain trolls venture this far South?
不是太久
Oh, not for an age…
从黑暗力量统制这些地方开始
Not since a darker power ruled these lands.
他们白天不能行动
They could not have moved in daylight.
附近肯定有个巢穴
There must be a cave nearby.
什么臭味？
Oh what's that stench?!
是山怪的地洞
It's a troll hoard.
别乱摸
Be careful what you touch.
就这样留这儿不太好吧
Seems a shame just to leave it lying around.
谁都可以来拿走
Anyone could take it.
十分同意
Agreed.
诺力 过来
Nori, come here.
拿铲子来
Get a shovel.
这些剑不是山怪铸造的
These swords are not made by any troll.
也不是人类铁匠铸造
Nor were they made by any smith among men.
这是在贡多林打造的…
These were forged in Gondolin…
第一纪元的最高级精灵打造
by the High Elves, of the First Age.
没有比这更好的刀刃
You could not wish for a finer blade.
奇力 来 过来
Kili, come, come.
好 快
Alright, come.
我们正在做一个长期存款
We're making a long-term deposit.
我们离开这个臭地方吧
Let's get out of this foul place.
走 我们走
Come on, let's go.
波佛 葛罗音 诺力
Bofur, Gloin, Nori.
- 比尔博 - 嗯？
- Bilbo. - Hm?
拿着 大小跟你刚合适
Here. This is about your size.
我不能接受这个
I can't take this.
这把剑是由精灵族铸造的 就是说…
The blade is of Elvish make, which means…
半兽人和妖精在附近的时候 它会发出蓝光
it will glow blue when orcs or goblins are nearby.
我之前从没用过剑
I- I have never used a sword in my life.
我也希望你永远不会用到它
And I hope you'll never have to.
但如果用到了 谨记：
But if you do, remember this:
真正的勇气不是何时去夺走一条生命…
True courage… is about knowing not when to take a life…
而是何时去饶恕一条生命
but when to spare one.
有东西在靠近
Something's coming!
甘道夫
Gandalf!
集合起来
Stay together.
赶快 他们带着武装
Hurry, they're armed!
带上武器
Arm yourselves!
小偷 纵火 杀人犯
Thieves! Fire! Murder!
瑞达加斯特
Radagast.
是褐袍巫师瑞达加斯特
It's Radagast the Brown!
你在找什么呢？
What on earth are you doing here?
我来找你 甘道夫
I was looking for you, Gandalf.
出事了 出大事了
Something's wrong. Something's terribly wrong!
什么事？
Yes?
让我想一想…
Just give me a minute, hm…
不…
No…
我有个想法 这会儿又忘了
I had a thought and, now I've lost it, it was-
都快到嘴边了 可它停留在舌头上了
it was was right there, on the tip of my tongue!
原来不是个想法
Oh! It's not a thought at all!
是个…
It's just only a…
竹节虫
stick insect.
绿林地病了 甘道夫
The Greenwood is sick, Gandalf.
黑暗笼罩了它 什么东西都不再生长
A darkness has fallen over it, nothing glows anymore.
至少好东西不再生长了
At least nothing good.
空气中满是腐臭味
The air is foul of decay,
但更糟的是那些网
but worse are the webs.
网？什么意思？
Webs? What do you mean?
蜘蛛 巨型蜘蛛
Spiders, Gandalf. Giant ones.
如果没看错的话 是安格利昂产的卵
Some kind of spawn of… Ungoliant, or I'm not a wizard.
我跟踪了它们
I followed their trail.
他们来自多尔哥多
They came from… Dol Guldur.
多尔哥多？
Dol Guldur?
但那古堡早已被废弃了
But the old fortress is abandoned.
没 甘道夫
No, Gandalf.
没被废弃
It is not.
一股黑暗力量住在那里
A dark power dwells in there…
但我之前从没察觉到
such as I have never felt before.
它是一个古老光环的影子
It is the shadow of an ancient aura.
能够召唤死人的幽灵
One that can summon the spirits of the dead.
我看到他了 甘道夫
I saw him, Gandalf.
在黑暗里
From out of the darkness…
死灵法师来了
the Necromancer has come!
不好意思
Sorry.
来口老托比烟
Try a little old Toby.
能让你平静下来
It'll help setting your nerves.
再吐出来
Then out.
那么…关于死灵法师
Now… the Necromancer.
你确定吗？
Are you sure?
它不是来自于活人的世界
That is not… from the world…of the living.
是狼吗？那里有狼吗？
Was that a wolf? Are there- are there wolves out there?
狼？
Wolves?
不 不是狼
No, that is not a wolf.
那是座狼侦察兵
Warg scouts!
意味着半兽人大军就在后边不远了
Which means an orc pack is not far behind.
半兽人大军？
Orc pack?
你把这个探险告诉同族之外的哪些人了？
Who did you tell about your quest, beyond your kin?
没有
No one.
到底告诉谁了？
Who did you tell?
没有 我发誓
No one, I swear!
到底他祖宗的怎么了？
What in Dorin's name is going on?
你被追击了
You're being hunted.
我们必须离开这里
We have to get out of here.
跑不了 我们没有马 它们脱缰了
We can't! We have no ponies. They bolted.
我可以把他们引开
I'll draw them off.
这些是刚达巴山座狼 它们能追上你
These are Gundabad wargs. They will outrun you!
这些是罗斯戈贝尔兔子
These are Rhosgobel rabbits.
我想可以试试
I'd like to see them try.
来抓我呀
Come and get me!
走
Come on!
靠在一起
Stay together.
欧力 不
Ori, no!
回来
Come back.
全部人前进 快 快点
All of you, come on, come on! Quick!
你要带我们去哪？
Where're you leading us?
矮人就在那里
跟着他们
快走
Move!
快跑
Run!
他们在那儿
There they are!
这边 快点
This way! Quickly!
他们会越来越多的
I think there's more coming!
奇力 射他们
Kili! Shoot them!
我们被包围了
We're surrounded!
甘道夫呢？
Where's Gandalf?
他抛弃我们了
He's abandoned us!
守住阵地
Hold your ground!
这边 一群笨蛋
This way, you fools!
快 快走
Com'on, move!
都赶紧 快
Quickly! All of you!
快 快 快
Go, go, go!
… 九个 十个…
…nine, ten…
奇力 快跑
Kili! Run!
是精灵族
Elves.
我看不到这条路通向哪儿
I cannot see where the pathway leads.
我们要往前走吗？
Do we follow it or no?
当然往前走
We follow it, of course!
我想这是明智的
I think that would be wise.
伊姆拉里斯峡谷
The valley of Imladris.
通常大家会叫他另一个名字
In the common tongue, it's known by another name.
瑞文戴尔
Rivendell.
这是坐落在大海东边最后的守护所
Here lies the last homely house, east of the sea.
这就是你的计划
This was your plan all along…
向我们的敌人寻求庇护
to seek refuge with our enemy.
在这里你没有敌人 索林·橡木盾
You have no enemies here, Thorin Oakenshield.
这峡谷里唯一的敌意就是你自己带来的
The only ill-will to be found in this valley is that which you bring yourself.
你觉得精灵族人会为我们的探险祈福吗？
You think the Elves… will give our quest their blessing?
他们会试图阻止我们
They will try to stop us.
他们当然会
Of course, they will.
但是我们有问题需要解答
But we have questions that need to be answered.
如果我们要成功 就需要策略
If we are to be successful, this will need to be handled with tact…
和尊重
and respect…
和一点魅力
and no small degree of charm.
所以你才需要让我来沟通
Which is why you will leave the talking to me.
米思兰迪尔
Mithrandir.
啊 林德
Ah, Lindir.
精神点
Stay sharp.
我听说你来河谷了
我必须与爱隆王交谈
I must speak with Lord Elrond.
爱隆王不在
My Lord Elrond is not here.
不在？
Not here?
那他在哪？
Where is he?
聚拢到一起
Close ranks!
甘道夫
Gandalf!
爱隆王
Lord Elrond.
我的朋友
你去哪儿了？
我们猎杀了一群来自南方的半兽人
在秘密隘口附近
半兽人这么靠近我们的边界真是奇怪
Strange for orcs to come so close to our borders.
某些东西或某个人招引他们来
Something or someone has drawn them near.
啊 那应该是我们了
Ah, that may have been us.
欢迎你索林 索恩之子
Welcome Thorin, son of Thrain.
我们没见过面吧
I do not believe we have met.
你有你祖父的仪态
You have your Grandfather's bearing.
索尔统治山下的时候我认识他
I knew Thror when he ruled under the mountain.
是吗？他没提到过你
Indeed? He made no mention of you.
他说什么？他在骂我们吗？
What is he saying? Does he offer us insult?
不是的 他说请我们吃饭
No Master Gloin, he's offering you food.
好吧
Ah Well…
那就带路吧
In that case, lead on.
尝尝 就一口
Try it. Just a mouthful.
我不喜欢绿色食物
I don't like green food.
肉呢？
Where's the meat?
他们有炸薯条吗？
Have they got any chips?
感谢你邀请我们 可我没有正装赴宴
Kind of you to invite us, I'm… not really dressed for diner.
你从没有穿上过
Well, you never are.
这是兽咬剑
This is Orcrist…
斩妖剑
the Goblin-cleaver.
著名的剑 由西方的高等精灵锻造
A famous blade, forged by the High Elves of the West.
我的同胞
My kin.
希望它能为你所用
May it serve you well.
这是格兰瑞
And this is Glamdring…
死敌之锤 贡多林国王的剑
The Foe-hammer, sword of the king of Gondolin.
这些剑是为第一纪元的妖精大战打造的
These swords were made for the Goblin wars of the First-
我不在乎 伙计
I wouldn't bother, laddie.
剑的命名源自于它们在大战中的伟大功绩
Swords are named for the great deeds they do in war.
你是在说 我的剑还没有经过战争的洗礼？
What're you saying, my sword hasn't seen battles?
我都不确定它是不是一把剑
I'm not actually sure it is a sword.
更像是把小刀 说真的
More of a letter opener, really.
你们怎么把这些剑带来了？
How did you come with these?
我们在东方大道上一个山怪的地洞里发现的
We found them in a troll hoard on the Great East road,
就在中半兽人的埋伏之前
shortly before we were ambushed by orcs.
那你们在东方大道上做什么？
And what were you doing on the Great East road?
我们的事与精灵族无关
Our business is no concern of Elves.
拜托 索林 给他看看地图
For goodness sake. Thorin, show him the map!
这是我的子民的遗产
It is the legacy of my people.
我有责任保护它
It's mine to protect!
包括其中的秘密
As are its secrets.
别再坚持你们矮人族的倔犟了
Save me from the stubbornness of dwarves.
你的骄傲会把你拽垮
Your pride will be your downfall.
中土世界能读懂这张地图的人屈指可数 你面前的算一个
You stand here in the presence of one of the few in Middle-earth who can read that map.
快给爱隆王看
Show it to Lord Elrond!
是伊鲁伯
Erebor.
你对这张地图的什么感兴趣？
What is your interest in this map?
主要是学术方面的
It's mainly academic.
你知道 这类史前古物中会经常暗藏文字
As you know, this sort of artifacts sometimes contains hidden texts.
你还能读古矮人语 对吧？
You still read ancient dwarvish, do you not?
是的 「色斯文·伊西尔」
Yeah, "Cirth ithil".
月符文
Moon runes…
当然了
Of course.
很轻易就会错过
An easy thing to miss.
这儿要想读到月符文 只能借助月光
And in this case, that is true. Moon runes can only be read by the light
而且月亮还要与写它的那一天具有相同的形状
of the moon of the same shape and season as the day on which they were written.
你能读到吗？
Can you read them?
写这些符文的时候是在一个仲夏前夕
These runes were written on a mid-summer's eve
新月的月光下 将近两百年前
by the light of a crescent moon nearly two hundred years ago.
看来你们注定要来瑞文戴尔
It would seem you were meant to come to Rivendell.
命运与你同在 索林·橡木盾
Fate is with you, Thorin Oakenshield.
今晚恰巧是同样的月光照耀着我们
The same moon shines upon us tonight.
「画眉袭来的时候靠到青石边上
"Stand by the grey stone when the thrush knocks,
夕阳带着杜林日落的余光
and the setting sun with the last light of Durin's Day
将照在钥匙孔上「
will shine upon the key-hole".
杜林日？
Durin's Day?
就是矮人族新年的开始
Which is the start of the dwarves' new year,
那天 秋季最后一天的月亮和冬季第一天的太阳…
when the last moon of Autumn and the first sun of Winter
会同时出现在天空
appear in the sky together.
这是个坏消息
This is ill news.
夏季马上就要过去 杜林日很快就来到了
Summer is passing. Durin's Day will soon be upon us.
我们还有时间
We still have time.
时间 做什么？
Time, for what?
找到入口
To find the entrance.
我们一定要到正确的地点 正确的时间
We have to be standing at exactly the right spot, at exactly the right time.
只有那时…门才能被打开
Then, and only then… can the door be opened.
所以这就是你们的目的 进入到山脉里
So this is your purpose. To enter the mountain.
那又怎样？
What of it?
有人觉得这不甚明智
There are some who would not deem it wise.
什么意思？
Who do you mean?
你们并非中土世界的唯一守护者
You are not the only guardian to stand watching over Middle-earth.
那些矮人 主人…
…我们跟丢了
被那些臭精灵伏击 我们…
我不要借口
我要矮人王的头
我们兵力不够
我们尽力了
我差点没命
你最好…
为此偿命
矮人很快会露面
放话出去
砍下他们的头有赏
庞博
Bombur!
不管我们帮不帮忙 矮人族都会向山脉行进
With or without our help, these dwarves will march on the mountain.
他们决心收回他们的领地
They're determined to reclaim their homeland.
我不认为索林·橡木盾觉得自己要对任何人负责
I do not believe Thorin Oakenshield feels that he's answerable to anyone.
- 我也不用 - 因为他们要回应的人不是我
- Nor for that matter am I. - Cause it's not me they must answer to.
盖拉德丽尔夫人
Lady Galadriel.
米思兰迪尔
Mithrandir.
好久不见了
岁月或许改变了我
但罗瑞安夫人却没变
我不知道爱隆王把您请来了
I'd no idea Lord Elrond had sent for you.
他没请
He didn't.
是我请的
I did.
萨鲁曼
Saruman.
你最近很忙啊 我的朋友
You've been busy of late, my friend.
告诉我 甘道夫
Tell me, Gandalf…
你不觉得你的计划和方案都会被忽视么？
Did you think these plans and schemes of yours would go unnoticed?
被忽视？
Unnoticed?
不 我觉得…
No, I…
我只是在做我认为正确的事情
I'm simply doing what I feel to be right.
你在那头恶龙上花了太多心思
The dragon… has long been on your mind.
是的 女士
It is true, my Lady.
史矛革不效忠于任何人
Smaug owes allegiance to no one.
但他若站在敌人那边
But if he should side with the enemy,
局势会变得很糟糕
the dragon could be used to terrible effect.
什么敌人？
What enemy?
甘道夫 敌人已经被打败了
Gandalf, the enemy is defeated.
索伦已经被打败了
Sauron is vanquished.
他不可能再回到他的全盛时期
He can never regain his full strength.
甘道夫…
Gandalf…
四百年了 我们都生活在和平中
for four hundred years, we have lived in peace,
但是和平中暗藏危机
a hard won watchful peace!
我们真的生活在和平中了么？
Are we- are we at peace?
巨魔从高山袭来
Trolls have come down from the mountains,
他们袭击村落 摧毁农庄
they are raiding villages, destroying farms.
半兽人在路上袭击我们
Orcs have attacked us on the road.
战争的序曲已经奏响
Hardly a prelude to war.
你总是多管闲事
Always you must meddle.
就爱无事生非
Looking for trouble where none exist!
让他说下去
Let him speak.
有一些比史矛革更邪恶的东西要应付
There is something at work beyond the evil of Smaug,
一些比史矛革更强大的东西
something far more powerful.
虽然我们可以对它视若无睹 但它不会放过我们
We can remain blind to it, but it will not be ignoring us, that I can promise you.
绿林下暗潮汹涌
A sickness hides over the Greenwood.
那里的伐木人称之为幽暗密林 他们说…
The woodsmen who live there now call it Mirkwook, and uh, they s- they say…
不要停 伐木人说什么了？
Well, don't stop now, tell us what the woodsmen say?
他们提及过居住在多尔哥多的死灵法师
They speak of a Necromancer, living in Dol Guldur,
可以召唤亡者的巫师
a sorcerer who would summon the dead.
这太荒诞了
That's absurd.
世上不存在这种力量
No such power exists in this world.
死灵法师也是凡人而已
This… Necromancer is nothing more than a mortal man.
只不过是研习黑魔法的巫师
A conjurer dabbling in black magic.
我曾经也是这么想 不过…
And so I thought too. But…
瑞达加斯特看见了
Radagast has seen
瑞达加斯特？
Radagast?
不要跟我提起褐袍瑞达加斯特
Do not speak to me of Radagast the Brown.
他是个蠢货
He's a foolish fellow.
他是个怪人 这点我同意 他一直独居
Well… he's odd, I grant you, he lives a solitary life.
这不是重点
It's not that.
是他蘑菇吃得太多了
It's his excessive consumption of mushrooms.
脑袋吃糊涂了 牙齿也吃黄了
They've addled his brain, and yellowed his teeth.
我警告过他
I warned him.
一个埃斯塔力（巫师）成员在深林游荡总不是什么好事
It is unbefitting one of the Istari wandering the wood…
你带了东西来
You carry something.
是瑞达加斯特给你的
It came to you from Radagast…
他在多尔哥多找到的
He found it in Dul Guldur…
是的
Yes.
让我看看
Show me.
这是什么？
What is that?
一件魔多遗物
A relic of Mordor.
魔窟剑
A Morgul blade…
它是为安格马的巫妖王打造的
Made for the witch-king of Angmar,
并已随他一起下葬
and buried with him…
当安格马沦陷时
when Angmar fell.
北方的人带走了他的尸体
The men of the North took his body,
他所有的东西都被封印在鲁道夫山上
and all that he possessed was sealed within the high fells of Rhudaur.
深葬于岩石的
Deep within the rock, they buried him…
黑暗墓穴中
in a tomb so dark…
他不可能重见天日的
it couldn't have come to light.
这不可能
This is not possible.
这些墓穴上有着强大的符咒 他们不可能被打开
A powerful spell lies upon those tombs, they cannot be opened!
我们有什么证据证明这把剑是来自安格马的墓穴？
What proof do we have this weapon came from Angmar's grave?
我没有
I have none.
因为根本没有
Because there is none.
我们来分析一下
Let us examine what we know.
一小撮半兽人穿过了布鲁南河
A single orc pack has dared to cross the Bruinen.
一把古剑重见天日
A dagger from a by-gone age has been found.
一个自称死灵法师的男巫
And a human sorcerer who calls himself the Necromancer,
出现在荒废的森林
has taken up residence in a ruined fortress.
这还不是最重要的
It's not so very much, after all.
这种矮人才让我困扰
The question of this dwarvish company however, troubles me deeply.
我不是很相信 甘道夫
I'm not convinced, Gandalf.
我不认为我能容忍这种事情
I do not feel I can condone such a quest.
如果他们来找我 我只好让他们失望了
If they come to me, I might just spare them this disappointment.
我不会假装能够理解你让他们燃起希望的理由
I will not pretend to understand your reasons for raising their hopes…
他们离开了
They are leaving.
是的
Yes.
你知道了
You knew.
我想没什么别的办法了
… I'm afraid there's nothing else for it.
爱隆阁下
My Lord Elrond.
这些矮人
The dwarves…
已经离开了
they've gone.
警惕点
Be on your guard,
我们要进入荒野边境了
we're about to step over the Edge of the Wild.
巴林 你熟悉路 带路吧
Balin, you know this path, lead on.
遵命
Ah Aye.
巴金斯大人
Master Baggins,
我建议你还是跟上的好
I suggest you keep up.
跟着他们
You will follow them.
是
Yes.
你帮助索林·橡木盾是对的
You are right to help Thorin Oakenshield.
但我担心这次探险惊动了一些我们未知的力量
But I fear this quest has set in motion forces we do not yet understand.
魔窟剑之秘必须解开
The riddle of the Morgul blade must be answered.
有些暗流在未知阴影中涌动
Something moves in the shadows, unseen,
它躲着我们
hidden from our side, it will not show itself…
还不愿露面
not yet.
但是它每天都在变强
But every day it grows in strength.
你必须小心谨慎
You must be careful.
是
Yes…
米斯兰迪尔
Mithrandir.
为什么选哈夫林（即霍比特人）？
Why the Halfling?
我不知道
I don't know.
萨鲁曼认为只有强大的力量才能震慑邪恶
Saruman believes that it is only a great power that can hold evil in check,
但我不相信
but that is not what I have found.
我觉得日常琐事
I found it is… the small things,
普通人每天的生活
everyday deeds of ordinary folk,
能够遏制黑暗
that keep the darkness at bay…
例如平凡的善与爱
simple acts of kindness and love.
为什么是比尔博·巴金斯？
Why Bilbo Baggins?
或许是他能给恐惧中的我带来勇气
Perhaps it is because I am afraid and he gives me courage.
不要怕 米斯兰迪尔
Do not be afraid, Mithrandir.
你并不孤单
You are not alone.
需要我帮助的时候
我就会出现
很好 坚持住
Alright, hold on!
我们一定要找个藏身之地
We must find shelter!
小心
Look out!
稳住
Hold on!
这不是暴风雨
This is no thunderstorms!
是雷霆之战
It's a thunder-battle!
看
Look!
保佑我吧
Well bless me.
传说都是真的
The legends are true!
巨人 岩石巨人
Giants! Stone giants!
找掩护 蠢货
Take cover, you fool!
等一下
Hold on!
奇力 抓住我的手
Kili, grab my hand!
怎么回事？奇力 抓住我的手
What's happening? Kili, grab my hand!
跑 跑啊 快跑
Run, run, run!
- 跑 跑啊 - 快跑 继续 坚持住
- Run, run, run!- Let's run! Come on, keep on.
不
Noooo!
不要
Nooo!
不要啊 奇力
No! Kili!
我们还好 我们还活着
We're alright! We're alive!
比尔博去哪儿了？
Where's Bilbo?
霍比特人去哪儿了？
Where's the hobbit?
抓住我的手
Grab my hand!
比尔博
Bilbo!
快 抓住
Come on and take it!
我抓住你了
I've got you, lad.
快 快
Come on, come on!
抓住他了
Get him!
我还以为把我们的飞贼弄丢了呢
I thought we'd lost our burglar.
不
No!
他一离开家就已经把自己弄丢了
He's been lost ever since he left home.
他根本就不该来
He should never have come.
我们当中没有他的位置
He has no place amongst us.
德瓦林
Dwalin!
看来很安全 看看周围
It looks safe enough. Search nearby.
这山里的洞穴很少没人住
Caves in the mountain are seldom unoccupied.
这里什么都没有
There's nothing here.
那就好 我们来生火吧
Right then. Let's get the fire started.
不 别生火 这里不行
No. No fires. Not in this place.
睡一觉吧
Get some sleep…
我们破晓出发
We start at the first light.
我们要在山上等到甘道夫过来
We were to wait in the mountains until Gandalf joined us.
这是原计划
That was the plan.
计划变了
Plans change.
波佛
Bofur…
你第一个值夜
Take the first watch.
刚留下的气味
他们去了大山隘口
好吧
Okay…
你要去哪儿？
Where do you think you're going?
回瑞文戴尔
Back to Rivendell.
不 你不能现在回去
No. No, you can't turn back, now.
你是团队的一部分 你是我们中的一员
You're part of the company. You're one of us.
我现在不是了？对吧？
I'm not now, am I?
索林说我不该来 他是对的
Thorin said I should never have come, and he was right.
我不是图克家的 我是巴金斯家的 我不知道我那时在想什么
I'm not a Took, I'm a Baggins, I don't know what I was thinking.
我真不该跑出来
I should've never ran out the door.
你只是想家了 我理解
You're homesick. I understand.
不 你不理解 你不理解 你们这些矮人
No, you don't! You don't understand, none of you do, you're dwarves!
你们都习惯了这种生活 颠沛流离
You're used to th- to this life, to living on the road,
居无定所 了无牵挂
never settling in one place, not belonging anywhere.
抱歉 我并不…
Oh, I'm sorry, I didn- hmm…
不 你是对的
No, you're right.
我们不属于任何地方
We don't belong anywhere.
祝你好运
I wish you all the luck in the world.
真的
I really do.
那是什么？
What's that?
醒醒
Wake up.
快醒醒
Wake up!
当心
Look out!
放开我 滚开
Leave my- go away!
把手拿开
Get your hands off me!
滚开
Get off me!
谁这么大胆敢带着武器来到我的领土？
Who would be so bold as to come armed into my kingdom?
是间谍？小偷？刺客？
Spies? Thieves? Assassins?
矮人 邪恶之人
Dwarves, your Malevolence.
矮人？
Dwarves?
我们在前门发现了他们
We found them on the front porch.
不要干站在那里 搜他们身
Well don't just stand there, search them!
每个头盔和箭袋都不要放过
Every crowns, every quivers!
你们在这里做什么？
What are you doing in these parts.
说
Speak!
好 既然他们不说
Very well, if they will not talk…
我们就让他们叫
we'll make them squawk!
把绞肉机抬上来 把碎骨机抬上来
Bring up the mangler, bring up the bone breaker.
从最年轻的开始
Start with the youngest.
等等
Wait!
好 好 好
Well well well!
看看是谁
Look who it is.
索林 索恩之子 索尔之孙
Thorin, son of Thrain, son of Thror,
山下之王
king under the mountain.
啊 我忘记你没有山了
Oh! But I'm forgetting you don't have mountain.
也不是国王 这样来说
And you're not a king. Which makes you…
你就什么也不是
nobody really.
我认识一个人… 他愿意为你的头出个大价钱
I know someone… who would pay a petty price for your head.
只是头
Just the head…
别的都不要
nothing attached.
或许你知道我在说谁
Perhaps you know of whom I speak.
你的老敌人了
An old enemy of yours…
白半兽人 骑着白狼
The Pale Orc… astride a white Warg.
毁灭者阿索格… 他已经死了
Azog the Defiler… was destroyed.
他在很久以前的战斗中就被杀死了
He was slain in battle long ago
所以你就觉得他的日子结束了 是么？
So you think his defiling days are done, do you?
告诉白半兽人
Send word to the Pale Orc,
跟他说我找到了他的宝贝了
tell him I have found his prize.
啊
Yesss.
不错
Yes!
Yes…
咕噜
Gollum…
好啊
Yes!
咕噜 咕噜
Gollum! Gollum!
恶心的… 妖精…
Nasty… Goblinses… are…
比老骨头好多了 宝贝
better than old bones, precious.
比什么都没有好
Better than… nothing.
啊 骨头太多了 宝贝
Aah, too many boneses, precious.
没多少肉
Not enough flesh.
闭嘴 把皮剥了
Shut up! Cut its skin off!
从头开始
Start with its head.
∮ 土地又冷又硬 他们咬我们的手 ∮
∮ The cold hard lands, they bites our hands ∮
∮ 咬我们的脚 ∮
∮ they gnaws our feet ∮
∮ 因为岩石都像老骨头 ∮
∮ for rocks and stones are like old bones ∮
∮ 全没有血肉 ∮
∮ all bare of meat ∮
∮ 和死亡一样冰冷 死了更好下口 ∮
∮ cold as death, without no breath it's good to eat ∮
保佑我们 宝贝
Bless us and splash us, precious,
一口下去都是肉
that's a meaty mouthful.
咕噜 咕噜
Gollum! Gollum!
退后 往后退
Back. Stay back.
我警告你 别过来
I'm warning you, don't come any closer.
他拿着精灵剑
It's got an Elfish blade,
但他不是精灵
but it's not an Elfes.
不是精灵 不是
Not an Elfes, no…
他是谁 宝贝？
Whot is it, precious?
他是谁？
Whot is it?
我的名字是
My name…
比尔博·巴金斯
is Bilbo Baggins.
巴金斯
Bagginses.
谁是巴金斯 宝贝？
Whot is a Bagginses, precious?
我是夏尔来的霍比特人
I'm a… hobbit from the Shire.
我们喜欢妖精 蝙蝠和鱼 但还没吃过霍比特人
We like goblinses, batses and fishes, but we hasn't try Hobbinses before!
很嫩吗？
Is it soft?
很多汁吗？
Is it juicy?
不 不 不
No! No, keep-
离我远点儿
Keep your distance!
如果有必要 我会用上这个东西
I'll use this. If I have too.
我不想惹麻烦 你明白么？
I don't-I don't want any trouble, you understand?
告诉我出去的路 然后我自己离开
Just show me the way to get out of here, and I'll be on my way.
为什么？他迷路了？
Why? Is it lost?
对 对 我想尽快找到回去的路
Yes. Yes, and I want to get unlost, as soon as possible.
我们知道霍比特人的安全出路 隐藏在黑暗中的路
Oh, we knows! We knows safe path for hobbitses. Safe path in the dark.
闭嘴
Shut up!
我什么都没说
I didn't say anything.
我不是在跟你说话
I wasn't talking to you!
是 宝贝 我们…
Oh yes, we- we was, precious, we was.
我不知道你玩什么游戏 不过我…
Look, I- I don't know what you're game is. but I-
游戏？
Games?
我们喜欢游戏 是吧 宝贝？
Oh we love games, doesn't we, precious?
他喜欢游戏么？
Does it like games?
他喜欢么？他喜欢玩儿么？
Does it, does it, does it like to play?
也许吧
Maybe.
什么东西有脚无人见
What has roots as nobody sees,
个子高高赛大树
Is taller than trees,
高耸入云霄
Up, up, up it goes,
但是从来不长个儿？
And yet never grows?
- 大山 - 是的 是的
- The moutain. - Yes, yes.
再来一个？
Let's have another one, uh?
好 你说吧
Yes. Go, do it again.
再来再来 问我们
Do it, do it again, ask us.
不 别猜迷了
No. No more riddles.
干掉他 快干掉他
Finish him off, finish him now!
咕噜 咕噜
Gollum, Gollum!
不 不 不
No! No, no.
我…我想玩儿
I w- I want to play.
我愿意 我想玩儿 我看得出来
I do. I want to play. I can see…
你肯定…
you are…
很擅长这个
very good at this.
所以 为什么我们…
So… why don't we…
不再来猜谜语呢
have a game of riddles.
只有你和我
Yes, just- just- just you and me.
不错
Nice.
就只有
Just…
你和我
Just- just us.
好 好
Yes. Yes!
如果我赢了
And- and if I win…
你给我带路出去
you will show me the way out.
行吗？
Yes?
好 好
Yes. Yes!
那要是你输了呢？
And if you loses, what then?
如果他输了 宝贝 我们就把他吃掉
Wow, if it loses, precious, we will eats it!
对 巴金斯输了 我们就把他吃掉
Yes, Baggins loses, we eats it all.
很公平
Fair enough.
巴金斯先来
The Baggins first.
红色山上有30匹白马
Thirty white horses on a red hill,
他们先细嚼
First they champ,
再跺脚
Then they stamp,
最后静静不动了
Then they stand still.
是牙齿？
Teeth?
牙齿
Teeth!
对 我的宝贝
That's my precious!
但我们… 我们… 只有…
But we… we… only have…
9颗
nine.
到我了
My turn.
它无声大喊
Voiceless it cries,
不翼而飞
Wingless flutters,
无牙而噬
Toothless bites,
无嘴而语
Mouthless mutters.
等一下
Just a minute.
啊
Oh, oh!
我们知道了 我们知道了
We knows, we knows!
闭嘴
Shut up!
是风 对 是风
It's wind! Course it is.
聪明的霍比特人
Very clever hobbitses,
真聪明
very clever!
无盖之盒
A- A box without hinges, key,
无链无匙
Or… or lid,
宝在其中
yet golden treasure inside is hid.
呃
Well?
真卑鄙
It's nasty.
你要放弃了么？
D'you give up?
给我们个机会 宝贝 给我们个机会
Oh, give us a chance, precious, give us a chance.
鸡蛋 是鸡蛋
Eggses! Eggses!
又湿又易碎的蛋 一定是
Wet, crunchy little eggses, yes yes,
奶奶教过我怎么吃他们
Grandmother, taught us to suck them, yes!
我们有了新的谜语
We have one for you.
它吞噬一切
All things it devours,
鸟 兽 树 花
Birds, beasts, trees, flowers,
吞钢嚼铁
Gnaws iron, bites steel,
磨石为粉
Grinds hard stones to meal.
回答吧
Answer us.
等一下 我刚给了你们那么长时间考虑
Give me a moment, please, I gave you a good long one.
我不知道
I don't know this one.
是不是很好吃？
Is it tasty?
是不是很美味？
Is it scrumptious?
松软么？
Is it crunchable!
让我想想
Let me think!
Let me think.
想不出
It's stuck!
巴金斯…
Bagginses…
想不出
Is stuck.
时间到
Time's up.
时间？时
Time? Ti-
答案是… 时间
The answer… is Time.
事实上 这谜语没那么难
Actually, it wasn't that hard.
最后一问
Last question…
最后一次机会
Last chance…
好吧
Okay… uh…
问吧
Ask us…
Ask us!
好 好的
Yes. Yes, alright.
我口袋里…
What have I got…
有什么东西？
in my pocket?
这不公平 这…
That's no fair. Is…
不公平 你犯规了
Is no fair. Is against the rules!
换一个问题
You ask us another one.
不 不 不换
No. No no no.
你说的 问你一个问题
You said, ask me a question.
这就是我的问题
Well that is… my question.
我口袋里有什么？
What have I got in my pocket?
猜三次 宝贝 他必须给我们三次机会
Three guesses, precious, he must give us three!
猜三次 好的 猜吧
Three guesses, very well, guess away.
手
Handses!
错了 再猜
Wrong. Guess again.
刀子
Knife!
不 闭嘴
Oh, shut up!
又错了 最后一次机会
Wrong, again. Last guess.
绳子
String!
或者什么都没有
Or nothing.
一次猜了两个
Two guesses at once.
但是都错了
Wrong both times.
所以…
So…
来吧
Come then.
我赢了 你答应过我给我带路
I won the game, you promised to show me the way out.
我们说过么 宝贝？
Did we say so, precious?
我们说过么？
Did we say so?
他口袋里有什么？
Whot has he got in his pocketses?
这不关你们事
That's no concern of yours.
你输了
You lost.
输了
Lost.
输了？
Lost?
它到哪里去了？
Uh where is it?
他到哪里去了？
Where is it?
不要
No!
它到哪里去了？不
Where is it? Nooo!
丢了 丢了
Lost, lost!
该死的
Curse us and splash us,
我的宝贝丢了
my precious is lost!
你丢了什么？
What have you lost?
不准问 不关你事
Mustn't ask us, not it's business,
不
Nooo!
咕噜 咕噜
Gollum! Gollum!
他的
What…
该死的口袋里
has he got…
到底有什么
in its nasty little pockets.
太晚了
It's too late.
太迟了
It's too late!
已经太迟了
∮ 骨头敲碎 脖子扭断 ∮
∮ Bones will be shattered, neck will be wrung ∮
∮ 严刑拷打 挂上刑架 ∮
∮ You'll be beaten and battered, from racks you'll be hung ∮
∮ 变成美餐 尸骨无存 ∮
∮ You will dine down here and never be found ∮
∮ 葬身于此 妖精之城 ∮
∮ Down in the deep of Goblin town ∮
我知道那把剑
I know that sword!
那是斩妖剑
It is the Goblin-cleaver!
噬人之刃
The Biter!
杀了成千上万的人
The blade that sliced a thousand neck,
砍他们 打他们 剥他们的皮 杀死他们
slash them, beat them, peel them, kill them all!
把他的头砍下来
Cut up his head!
拿起武器
Take up arms…
上
Fight.
Fight!
他使用死敌之锤 和阳光一样刺眼
He wields the Foe-hammer, the Beater, bright as daylight!
跟我来
Follow me.
快
Quick!
跑
Run!
把它给我们
Give it to us!
它是我们的
It's ours.
It's ours!
小偷
Thiefs!
巴金斯
Baggins!
快
Quickly!
不要停下来
Don't stop.
一 二
One! Two!
稳住
Post!
冲
Charge!
把绳子砍断
Cut the ropes!
快 快
Come on, quickly!
快点儿
Come on!
跳
Jump!
快点儿
Come on!
你们觉得你们能从我这里跑掉？
You thought you could escape me.
你现在要做什么呢 巫师？
What you gonna do now, wizard?
噢 不
Oh no!
这样做就行了
Well that will do it.
噢 还有更糟的时候
Oh, that could have been worse.
你在开玩笑吧
You've got to be joking!
甘道夫
Gandalf!
太多了 我们打不过他们
There's too many, we can't fight them.
只有一样东西能救我们
Only one thing will save us.
阳光
Daylight!
快
Come on!
这里 站好
Here, on your feet.
等等… 宝贝
Wait… my precious.
等等
Wait!
咕噜 咕噜
Gollum! Gollum!
巴金斯
Baggins!
小偷
Thief!
诅咒他 诅咒他 我们永远失去它了
Curse it and crush it, we lost it for ever!
五 六 七 八…
Five… Six… Seven… Eight…
毕佛… 波佛 十个
Bifur… Bofur… that's ten,
菲力 奇力… 十二个
Fili, Kili… that's twelve,
庞博 十三个了
And Bombur, that makes thirteen.
比尔博呢？
Where's Bilbo?
霍比特人呢？
Where is your hobbit?
我们的霍比特人呢？
Where is our hobbit?
该死的半身人
Curse that Halfling!
他不见了？我还以为和朵力在一起
Now he's lost? I thought he was with Dori!
别怪我
Don't blame me!
你最后一次看到他是在哪里？
And where did you last see him?
我好像在咱们第一次被困住的时候就看到他溜走了
I think I saw him slip away when they first cornered us.
到底怎么回事？告诉我
And what happened exactly? Tell me!
我来告诉你
I'll tell you what happened.
巴金斯大人看到机会就趁机溜走了
Master Baggins saw his chance and he took it!
从他踏出家门的时候
He's thought of nothing but his soft bed and his warm hearth
他就一直惦记家里的软床和壁炉
since first he stepped out of his door.
我们再也不会看到霍比特人了
We will not be seeing our hobbit again.
他走了很久了
He is long gone.
不
No…
他没有
he isn't.
比尔博·巴金斯
Bilbo Baggins…
我从没因为见到一个人而这么高兴
I've never been so glad to see anyone in my life.
比尔博… 我们以为你走了
Bilbo… We'd given you up!
你是怎么从妖精群中逃脱的？
How on earth did you get past the goblins?
到底怎么回事？
How indeed?
那有什么关系？
Oh, why does it matter?
他回来了
He's back.
有关系
It matters.
我想知道
I want to know…
你为什么回来？
why did you come back?
我知道你一直质疑我 一直
I know you doubt me. I know- I know you always have.
你说得对 我常想回去
And you're right, I often think of Bag End.
我怀念我的书
I miss my books…
我的摇椅 我的花园
and my arm chair, and my garden.
我就属于那个地方
See, that's where I belong.
那是我的家
That's home.
我回来的原因是
And that's why I came back, cause…
你们没有家
you don't have one. A home.
它被抢走了
It was taken from you.
但我会尽一切所能帮你夺回来
But I will help you take it back if I can.
追上他们
把他们扯成碎片
才出虎穴
Out of the frying pan.
又入狼窝
And into the fire.
跑
Run.
快跑
Run!
爬到树上去 所有人
Up into the trees. All of you!
快爬 比尔博 快爬
Come on, climb, Bilbo. Climb!
他们来了
They're coming!
阿索格
Azog!
你闻到了吗？
恐惧的气味
我记得你的父亲就散发过这种气味
索林 索恩之子
不可能…
It cannot be…
那个是我的
干掉其他的
喝光他们的血
菲力
Fili!
不
No!
Aah no!
喔不
Oh no!
甘道夫先生
Mister Gandalf!
稳住 诺力
Hold on, Nori!
不
Nooo!
索林 不
Thorin! No!
把那矮人的头给我砍来
杀了他
索林
Thorin!
Thorin.
我失败了么？
Have I failed?
这是你的权利
It's your right.
比尔博在这里 他很安全
Bilbo is here. He's quite safe.
你
You!
你疯了吗？
What were you doing?
你不知道你可能会把自己害死么？
You know you could've yourself killed?
我说过你是个累赘
Did I not say that you would be a burden?
你不可能在荒野里活下来的
That you would not survive in the wild…
我们当中没有你的位置
and you had no place amongst us.
我一生中从未错得如此离谱
I have never been so wrong, in all my life.
很抱歉曾经怀疑过你
Well, I'm sorry I doubted you.
不 其实我也怀疑我自己
No, I- I would have doubted me too.
我不是英雄 不是战士
I'm not a hero… nor a warrior.
甚至连飞贼都不算
Not even a burglar.
那是什么？你觉得那是什么？
What's that? What do you think it is?
伊鲁柏
Ereborn!
孤山
The Lonely Mountain.
中土世界最后的矮人王国
The last of the Great Dwarf Kingdoms of Middle-earth.
我们的家
Our home.
渡鸦
A raven!
鸟儿归山了
The birds are returning to the mountain.
那是一只画眉
That, my dear Oin, is a thrush.
那是一个好兆头
We will take it as a sign…a good omen.
你是对的
You're right.
我相信最坏的时候已经过去了
I do believe the worst is behind us.